我們這次邀請到 Imperial Games 42
Imperial 42 Games 的 Dylan 跟 Elsa
他們是一個跨國團隊
然後夫妻倆剛好在台灣
他們做的是一款類似像人狼的那種
需要用言語交談來推理的遊戲
So I'm Dylan, this is Elsa.
We're with Imperium 42 Game Studio.
And we made Throne of Lies.
And so right now it's for PC, Mac, and Linux.
And today I'm going to be telling you
about what I did right, what I did wrong,
and some general information that can help you
as indie developers.
So to start, I'm gonna show you what we started.
So when we first started, this is what it looked like.
It was pretty sad.
So this is when we were sort of experimenting a little bit.
This was very early stage here.
And then, now, this is about two years later, suddenly.
This is our thirty-second trailer, when we launched.
So we're, uh...
We're a 3D social production game.
And this means that there are good guys and bad guys,
and the good guys have to figure out who the bad guys are.
And in this game, it's online.
There's 16 players.
And you have some unique features
like drawing death notes.
It's all online.
It's done by a team of, we have a team of eight,
and the actual programmers are two.
I'm one of the programmers,
and the other programmer is in the United States.
And to get started, let's go.
So I told you a little bit about who I am generally.
I'm American.
I'm half British.
I've been living here with my wife, Elsa,
for about three years now.
I know that in Taiwan, cyber cafes are everywhere,
sort of like as often as you see Starbucks.
But in America, that's a very small thing.
I actually ran the first gaming cafe in South Carolina.
And so there I programmed some of our apps,
and then eventually I worked for the company
that ran our gaming cafe software.
And that was called Smart Launch at the time.
After that I went to Hawaii, where I met Elsa.
I went there for educational purposes.
And eventually I came to Taiwan.
And in between I worked all kinds of developer jobs.
I've done websites, back end, front end, full stack.
You know, just a bunch of little things.
Nothing really significant that I could really tell you.
Eventually, I didn't like my job, which is pretty much everyone's story, I'm sure.
And so I started programming a game on the side.
And that's when we launched Imperium 42.
So, Throne of Lies is our first game.
I told you a bit about it, you saw the trailer. It's made with Unity.
Right now it's Windows, Mac, Linux, maybe VR in the future, who knows.
Right now we have about 42,000 downloads in four months, so that's pretty good.
We only launched in October.
It's very similar to Town of Salem, if you've played that, or this game,
which is a popular mobile game that you guys may be familiar with.
So to start, I knew no Unity.
I knew nothing.
But I made some text adventure games with BB.net a while back.
And I like gaming, obviously.
But I didn't know where to start.
It's sort of overwhelming.
So eventually, I went to a Unity class.
And even though my Chinese is terrible,
and I was still able to absorb everything in the class.
Unity is in English.
And so this really helped me.
In cram school, opposed to just a regular education,
they really push through really fast.
So suddenly, in just a few months,
I made just a little online zombie shooter.
And from there, I felt really confident.
So I started making a game on the side.
I was still working full time as a developer, remotely.
So what ended up happening was I realized that.
I needed help, I couldn't do it by myself if I wanted this to be a real game, and I did it.
I'll talk more about finding people later,
but for now, we also did a...
I've been through a Kickstarter.
We successfully funded $21,000, we asked for $20,000.
I'll also be talking more about Kickstarter tips later on if you're interested in something like that.
I started off as just
by myself, and then eventually, I told you I needed help, I found a partner.
And...
He's a developer in the United States.
He is the only other programmer.
And once you have two, it starts getting official.
You start feeling it.
And then eventually, management.
And management is something that a lot of people don't
expect, but it sort of comes your way.
Suddenly, I'm developing less.
I want to develop more, but I have to manage.
So you have to think about legal, and hiring, and HR,
which I passed on to her, luckily.
Yeah, so if you have.
If you have a partner, then ask for a wife, a spouse,
or something that really helps too,
if it lays off some of the burden.
I used to do C Sharp.
I used to do VB.net when I started.
Now it's sort of a dead language.
No one uses that.
That's why we got taught in school.
VB.net, C Cool.
So I threw all that aside. Now I'm doing C-sharp JavaScript with Node mostly, like vanilla JavaScript.
No SQL. No SQL is the future. No one really uses SQL anymore, unless it's really an old database no one wants to migrate to.
I do a lot with APIs in DevOps. DevOps is sort of new to me, but APIs.
You guys, don't be afraid of APIs. They're your friends.
So like, you have Twitch and Discord and all these APIs.
to help you. You don't have to reinvent the wheel. So search for open source stuff first
as a template, or API stuff for doing anything you want. They usually have really good documentation.
So I'm going to teach you how to run a worldwide studio. What you do is, it's overwhelming,
so you start with one, and then you find more.
And so where do you find more?
I'm going to talk about that really soon.
But what you do want to do is when you hire people, you want
to give them the rules up front.
This is something you guys can definitely learn
from my mistakes.
So you want to have a contract at the very beginning.
You can Google free templates.
You don't have to hire a lawyer or spend any money.
Just Google it and edit it just a little bit.
You want to have the expectations up front.
You want to tell them they need to work x hours per week.
And they need to deliver in this type of way.
They need to communicate.
They must check in once every two days or three days.
You need to tell them what's up.
And this is where management comes in.
You really need to be strict on this, especially
at the beginning, because that's what sets the template.
You don't want to be stepped on.
You need to give them deadlines.
At the beginning, you're not going
to know what the deadlines are.
You're going to say, oh, I have no idea how long this takes
to make.
But what you're going to do is you're going to make a deadline anyway.
You're going to guess.
So you're going to say, three days, two weeks, it doesn't matter.
Eventually, you'll start to learn how long things should take.
And if they need to extend it, they'll tell you.
This is also a good way to see if you can trust your employees.
Because if you're working remotely like I am,
then you've never met these people before.
And that's where it comes to trials.
Trials, what you can do is when you hire someone new,
especially remotely, give them a 30 day trial.
When you have 30 days, you can make sure
that they perform exactly the way you want them to perform.
And if something goes wrong, you could say, sorry guys,
that's the end of the trial.
This was a trial run.
It also gives you sort of an excuse
to be sort of hard on them.
Because the beginning is everything.
And that's how you can tell if you trust them or not.
Communication is the most important,
especially for remote teams.
But even if you're in person, it's remote.
Communication is top key.
So Discord is what we use as the number one.
So Discord has really changed our development cycle
in the form of, we have one public one
and one private one.
So the private one is internal for the company.
So we have.
a news section, we have a high level to do, we have a section for PR, marketing, legal,
development, and you can code bots for that too, I'll talk about that later.
You can also use Trello.
If you guys have not used Trello before, it's sort of a scrum, agile type board.
It pretty much contains lists.
Actually I think I have it pulled up here, I can just show you what it looks like.
Where's my mouse?
There we go.
So you can organize it in different sections.
You can see a little bit of secrets that we're doing.
So we have a big backlog dump of things.
This should be tons of stuff.
Any time you think of it, just write it down.
Move it to things coming soon, even sooner.
And then you can assign it to whoever
with different priority levels and then drag it to done.
It's pretty satisfying to see done.
So trust is a big deal and that's why trials are really important.
You want to keep your promises.
And if you can't keep a promise, that's the point of the communication.
So if you feel like you're starting to become sick, give a warning to the team.
If you're coming up on a deadline and you don't think it's realistic, tell them.
Everyone can be very...
Very forgiving. As long as you communicate, then everything is under control.
It doesn't matter so much if you're late, it just matters that if you're late and nobody knows, that's when people get upset.
So, that said, you should work as a team and be understanding of each other, because eventually you'll have things that come up too.
And as long as they're not making excuses every single week, then I think it's okay.
You can find the humor in cross-culture issues.
So, we have an artist in India, and sometimes we have the communication barrier.
And so, sometimes I'll explain what I want to see in an art illustration.
And sometimes it doesn't come the way I want it.
So, what I end up doing is, instead of telling him in English what I want,
I mean, I'll tell him in English for the basics,
but I'll launch up MS Paint, and I'll doodle something,
and show him a picture of my paint.
So, and it ends up being really funny.
I actually save it.
Sometimes, you know when you see those memes with a horse,
where he says, how to draw a horse,
and it shows just some basic drawing,
and then a full, like, beautiful horse?
Yeah, something like that.
It gets pretty funny.
But yeah, because it can be frustrating too, you know?
So, you gotta find the humor in it,
because that's the way to go.
And when you're talking about teammates and management,
you need to learn to move on or adapt.
At first, try to adapt, and then move on.
So it could be said about gameplay elements.
Let's say you really want gameplay elements to work.
Like for example, you can see in our trailer,
they can draw death notes.
They can draw on that.
And so at first, we couldn't figure out
how to send it over the multiplayer network
so that everyone can see the same image.
And then at first, we were going to abandon it.
But then we just.
We knew that it was a lot of code to swap methods.
And so we did that, and we adapted, and it worked.
But some things don't work, and sometimes you just
have to move on and accept that.
And I said earlier, the same thing can apply to staff.
So let's say you hire someone.
In our case, PR guys, we find, are the hardest
to hire that are real.
And so sometimes you'll hire someone,
and their expectations don't meet your requirements.
and what you do is you can try to adapt, try to, you know,
what we do is we have a software we use called Time Doctor,
which is really useful for remote work.
It's like $10 a month,
and you can track their time and stuff.
You can, they'll take screenshots.
It's a little bit intrusive,
but usually we use it for disciplinary action.
Anyway, if that doesn't work, you have to move on.
You have to get rid of them, respectfully, of course,
and then try to find someone new.
For example, our PR guy, we had to get rid of him.
We got someone new.
And he was amazing.
He's been doing great.
Our engagement went up.
All this stuff, if we would have done this a long time ago,
then there wouldn't be any stress.
So yeah.
I mentioned earlier about Trello.
Scrum and Agile tactics are important,
because you really need to keep track.
of what everyone is doing.
It's also good for morale to see priority levels
and who is working on what.
So when you see that everyone else is working together,
it really raises morale for the entire team.
And then it also means you don't have to really ask questions
what people are doing, like you're poking them.
Sometimes some people don't like that.
Of course, you can ask what they're doing,
but you don't have to, which is sort of nice.
So all the developers here, the software developers,
the programmers, you probably know about Git.
But you may not know about GitLab.
Most people use GitHub.
That's sort of the flagship.
But GitLab has been an amazing experience.
You get 10 gigabytes for free, unlimited private repos,
and you can host your own GitLab on your VPS
if you use AWS, DigitalOcean, Google.
And so.
They also have support for continuous integration,
and that's also free.
This means that they have support for, if you push
and you have a special keyword, you
can make it so that it will automatically compile for you
and push to Steam or something.
So you have automatic building and automatic uploading,
which is super nice.
That's something that we haven't done yet,
but we really, really want to.
And so you've got to look at the future.
So if you want something like that, use GitLab instead of GitHub.
Reddit has been a big part of our life.
We like reddit.com slash r slash gamedev.
And here you can find so much for free.
I'm talking about music.
Any time someone goes to GDC, a group of open source composers
we'll put together a bunch of royalty-free music.
And when I say a bunch, I mean like 500 gigabytes
worth of free music and sounds, sound effects, everything,
and art.
So you can get so many things there.
And what you want to do is, especially when you're starting,
you can just use placeholders.
I mean, you don't have to have the final product
at the beginning, especially since at the beginning,
you just want to prototype and show off the product
to get more.
teammates and maybe investors or something.
So for
when you're hiring staff, there's also a game dev branch called game dev classifieds.
That's where I actually found half of my team.
So I mean
just going from this to this reddit place and hiring someone just really, you know, the game wouldn't exist without it.
We had a zero budget.
when we started Throne of Lies.
Zero.
So what we did was
we did profit sharing.
So we'll say if you work
every three hours per week
you work on Throne of Lies,
you get 1% of the company
profits.
So this encourages people.
But it doesn't encourage everyone.
It's not for everyone.
If you're on, for example,
GameDevClassifieds,
you're already expecting...
Profit sharing.
So you can launch a game like Throne of Lies
and not pay a penny until you actually
start making some money.
So especially if you have a remote team.
I work at home.
I don't have an office fee to pay.
And the remote staff, profit share,
it really helps if your budget is not huge.
And that said, you should still have some savings
before you start.
because yeah, you will find unexpected things.
And the more money you have saved, the more secure you'll feel.
And if you have a spouse, the more secure they'll feel too.
You know, because if you suddenly say you're quitting your full-time job to
make a video game, you may get some weird looks.
But yeah, so before I quit, I made sure that I had savings.
we had staff. I made sure that we had a small scope.
And so, when I say small scope, I mean, I wouldn't recommend going out and making your
first video game an MMO. That's huge. And when you're hiring people, people aren't
likely to follow you because they can't see the light at the end of the tunnel. You need
something where you can see from A to B.
In our case, Throne of Lies, we know that it's a tabletop game.
It's just one room.
And you can have other rooms, but it's
mostly focused on one room.
And I can list everything about the game on a Google Doc.
If you can't do that, your scope is too high.
So be sure to just list the high-level architecture, which
I'll list soon.
And so this is sort of fluff talk, but if you're
If you're stuck, just keep researching.
Don't give up.
Google has all the answers to everything.
And you may be stumped for, maybe you just put a comma in
the wrong place or something.
It's the same thing.
All programmers, especially, can speak for this.
You usually find the answer by realizing you
did something stupid.
So we found that DigitalOcean has been really useful for
our experience.
especially for an online game.
But even if you have an offline game, it can be very useful.
So if you have a VPS, DigitalOcean is cheaper
and gives you more stuff, and is more simple than AWS and Google.
And I highly recommend it.
In our case, we started off with a discourse forum.
Because whether you have an online or offline game,
you want people talking about your game.
You want people discussing it.
And so Discourse is a Ruby-based forum.
It's very live and active.
And it's free, which is most important.
I pay $20 a month for my DigitalOcean
and have this Discourse.
And it's like a forum, but it's all live.
So you can see people typing a response.
You can paste images directly in.
You don't have to refresh to see conversation flowing.
Twitter uses it.
EVE Online uses it.
It's good stuff.
So I want to talk about back end as a service, BaaS.
So most people think this is only useful for online games.
I'm going to say it's not.
I'm going to say it's useful for both.
Because this is cloud storage.
So what you can do is you can store stats in the cloud.
You can store authentication information.
You can store things that people may use.
So in our example, people will log in through Steam.
And when they log in through Steam, it goes to GameSparks.
And from there, they have our internal ID.
And from there, we can link it to anything.
We can say log in with Twitch or Facebook or anything.
And that means we can link it to other things
outside of the game.
So for this, you can consider meta stuff.
So for example, we can have our website.
pull stats from the game.
We can say, who has the most points?
Who has the most kills?
Who has the highest level of number of achievements?
And these are things you can find in offline games, too.
And for online games, they also have server-side support.
Or if you're a single-player game, you want some DRM,
you don't want your game to end up on Pirate Bay,
then this is something that you can
choose for server-side stuff.
So in our case, we can use it to make sure people don't cheat.
We can make sure that for multiplayer games,
it's not OK for people to cheat because it ruins other people's experience.
For single-player games, you might not care.
You guys should market early.
And if you've been to developer conferences,
this is probably something you hear in every single one.
It's very true.
There are ways to do it very efficiently.
I know you guys want to just jump into the game, but this is sort of a requirement.
Because you don't want to have this awesome game and nobody knows about it.
So, what you can do is you can make a single website and have just one hero banner.
You can hire someone on Fiverr.com, which I mention in a little bit.
Fiverr.com, you spend $5, $10, and you can get some really awesome stuff.
Some of it's sort of, you know, template-y. It's like a template, but...
They're all very nice and some of them are very legit. You can get voiceovers. Actually, I have it pulled up
For like five bucks you can get logo design you can get like a single page page website voiceover
We have our original Kickstarter trailer had a two-minute voiceover
I paid $20 for it and the guy sounded amazing the guy sounded like some celebrity. Oh, it was great
You think that voiceovers are really expensive?
They're not.
Go to Fiverr.com.
This is an awesome site for some things you've got to beware.
Some of the services are just terrible.
But half of them are amazing, and they'll
save you tons of money.
Yeah.
So let me go back to my slide here.
So when you market earlier, you have your single page website, you have all your social
media set up like Twitter and Instagram. Instagram's getting really popular lately, we realized.
And have it all linked to your website. You have a sign-up form with just only asking
for first name and email, nothing else. Now, 100% ask for first name because as a new company,
your email is going to be sent to spam.
And they have huge filters.
If Google doesn't recognize you, or Yahoo,
whatever you use, you'll be sent the spam 50% of the time.
So when you say their first name, like, hi, first name,
hi, Dylan, it goes through the filters.
Google thinks, hey, you know this person, so we're going to
go through, even if you're new.
So this is something you want to do.
Also, email lists have value to you and also for future games.
You can say, hey, you played our first game.
Check out our second game.
You can think it for the future.
OK, so we're at high level architecture.
I mentioned earlier about the game.
You should be able to structure it in a Google document
properly.
But the same should be done with your company.
So with that, you can just do that with a press kit.
And so a lot of times, if you Google for press kit templates,
you'll see press kit with parentheses.
That's old.
Don't use that.
That one uses PHP, and it's sort of dated.
You can use differently.
This differently is sort of a futuristic one.
You can find it.
It's open source on GitLab.
For example, our press kit looks like this.
It looks just like the old press kit with the parentheses.
I think they call it doPressKit.
And so it's structured just very simply.
It's really easy.
It's templated.
All you need to do is replace their text with your own.
And while you're doing this, something
that really helps get yourself exposed to Twitch and YouTube
is offer cutouts.
Check this out.
So we have art cutouts, and we send these
to our content creators.
And this is useful for even bloggers, too.
Anyone that makes any content for your game,
they have high quality assets.
So if I click this, it's going to be
a giant, high resolution image, which is probably
going to take forever to load.
And so it's huge.
You can't see it, but it's transparent.
So they can use it on whatever article, or if they're
making, you know, YouTube, they have the thumbnails.
They can make it effortlessly, over and over.
And that encourages them to play your game.
So a lot of people need support for their game.
And for that, you can use Freshdesk.
Freshdesk is a.
support desk service, and it's free.
And what's special about them is that you can have a support email,
like support at imperium42.com,
and the email will turn into a ticket automatically.
So that's really easy, so you can get your whole team to collaborate with each other.
And you can have, there's also private notes and automated things,
like if you have a scammer emailing you saying,
please give me 20 keys, then you can...
you can have an automated response based on certain keywords and stuff.
So there's always communication going with tickets.
So everyone knows what's happening at the same time.
So let's say you're busy, you say,
Elsa, please look at this ticket.
Then she'll go and she'll already know what's going on.
There's no information ever lost between the agents looking at the support tickets.
Buffer is amazing.
will queue up your post for social media and send it to all the social media platforms
at the same time.
So let's say you have, it's a pain, right?
You're doing Twitch, Facebook, Instagram, I think they have others too even, like Pinterest,
all the other little ones no one cares that much about.
But you can have them, and you queue up your post and it'll send it at the times that Buffer
thinks is the perfect time.
for you to send them. It'll automatically space it out for you.
So let's say, in our case, the best time to send it out is 2am because we target America.
And so, if we go like, 2am, I'm not going to stay up until 2am and post it.
But, I can queue it up to buffer, and I can queue it up many times.
I can queue up maybe 10 posts at a time.
So I queue up 10 at a time, and it'll send it out to Twitter, Instagram, Facebook,
all at 2am automatically.
So this is good stuff.
And if you add multiple, it will automatically space it out.
Buffer.com. It's free, too.
I'm not going to talk much about ads, but if you do do ads,
in our experience, the best thing to look out for is don't do pay-per-view.
That's just... that's meant for companies like Coke, Coca-Cola,
that want brand recognition.
But you don't want brand recognition.
I mean, it's nice, but you want conversion.
You want people to click on your ad and buy the game.
I mean, if they know it but don't buy it,
it shouldn't matter to most of you.
So pay per click.
You can track this stuff.
You can track most of the conversions.
Although, if you use Steam, it's sort of hard
to see if it works or not.
So I still don't recommend it that much.
But if you do it, do that.
GIFs and videos work the best for these types
when we're looking at engagements.
So what have I learned?
Read the fine print.
Now, when you launch that online game,
you launch World of Warcraft or something,
and you see the big terms of service,
I know everyone just skips past that.
But now you're in management, so you need to read this stuff.
So for example, we were choosing between our back end of service.
And at the time, we chose PlayFab.
for our very first one, before GameSparks.
And before that, as we're working on that,
I spent about a year of development
adding them into the game.
It was supposed to be $10 a month.
And then when we launched, I got the contract.
And so maybe about two weeks before we launched,
I got the contract.
I read it over.
And suddenly, I realized I'm not paying $10 a month
once I launch.
I'm paying $300 a month once I first launch.
And for a company with no budget.
If you've launched with Steam before, you don't get paid for even two months.
You have to wait two months and then you get paid.
I want to explain FinePrint in Chinese.
Sure.
FinePrint is a document that you have to read carefully.
Yeah, so we thought we were paying $10 a month.
Now we're paying $300 a month, US dollars.
So that's a big difference.
And so we couldn't afford that.
And so we ended up having to spend 150 hours to port
to the competitor, GameSparks.
And in the end, I did look ahead.
And they said that they would give me a free account,
since we were a very small team.
And so you guys can do that, too.
If you go to gamesparks.com and you have a small team,
small as in full-time, you can get a free Gamesparks BaaS account.
As long as you have under 100,000 people per month,
which is a lot, we don't even have half that,
then you get it for free, with no limitations.
It's awesome.
So as for PR firms, a lot of people, they wonder if they need PR or not.
And the answer is probably no.
Almost every time.
The PR guys, what I just taught you earlier about Buffer and all that, they're using that.
You can do that.
It seems like they're doing a lot, but all they do is they know the tools.
And we actually hired a PR firm at the beginning for our Kickstarter, and we spent about $1
We spent too much. We spent like $2,000 US dollars,
$3,000 US dollars, which was all of our budget on PR.
And so this ended up being a mistake.
So in the end, I realized that people, bloggers and news people for gaming,
they don't really care about Kickstarters.
You know, people have Kickstarters so often these days that it's just not news anymore.
And so many Kickstarters don't actually come into real games.
So people are afraid to cover you if you have a Kickstarter.
It may be better if you're new, if you actually launched.
But even then, you can actually Google for press release
companies instead.
And you pay maybe $45, maybe $50 US, and they
will distribute out to maybe hundreds, thousands of emails and companies.
You can do this yourself for $50 instead of $3,000.
Because just what I told you, this is what they do.
They know the tools, they know the sources.
And if you know what to Google, you can do it for so much cheaper.
So just skip PR firms.
If you're going to do a PR firm anyway, at least go to their website.
They'll always have client lists.
then contact those developers directly.
So somebody recently contacted me,
because we're on their website still.
They asked me, what do you think about these guys?
We're about to spend a few thousand.
And we didn't have very good things to say.
And so we may have saved them some money.
So you want to set your public milestones two weeks
after you're ready.
We made a mistake.
So when we launched our Alpha for the first time, we launched on the same day we were ready.
We said, we think we're going to be ready by this day?
Well, we were, literally.
So there was no buffer time in between.
What ended up happening was we were in a rush, we couldn't sleep,
we had to test a million miles an hour, we were stressed.
It was a very stressful time.
If we would have set our launch date maybe two weeks, or even a month after we're ready,
we could polish it a little bit, we could take our time to test it.
Lots of times there's always something small that,
something small maybe takes five minutes to change, but may have a big impact.
For example, let's say you have a tutorial and your tutorial button didn't work or something,
then just an extra little bit of time after you think you're ready.
it really makes a difference, not just for the players,
but for your whole team and your body.
We use Wikia for our documentation, our rules,
our external localization.
We don't have localization in the game yet.
I know I'm surprised that you guys showed up,
because we don't have Chinese localization yet.
So thank you guys for coming.
So it's pretty embarrassing, but we do have external localization right now.
And so what I mean by that is, I think I have Wikia pulled up, I do.
So here's the English one.
We actually have our community translate for us.
Because in exchange, we give them free keys.
Some of them just do it for free.
Some of them just do it because they're passionate about the game.
So you can see it's just a dump of documentation.
We have charts here. If it's in red, the page doesn't exist yet.
If it's in blue, then the page does exist.
And so some of it is in an English template.
You can see it's still in English, even though this is the Chinese page.
But you can see people are slowly editing section by section about the game.
So localization is a big project.
And you don't have to have it in game right at the beginning.
What you can do is, while you're programming,
you can ask the community to help you localize.
So when we do localize, everything is here.
And what are they working for?
You can give them game keys I mentioned earlier.
You can give them titles if you use Discord, or even in game.
You can give them something special.
In Discord, it takes two seconds to add them a title,
but they're stoked about it.
We give them a secret channel called Wikia Masters.
And so only the Wikia people that contribute and localize
can see this channel in Discord.
It's huge for morale.
They think it's super cool, and they're part of the community.
They're engaged.
And sometimes they compete to see
who has the highest edit counts, which is a win-win, you know?
It's a wonderful thing.
And so we actually have quite a lot of translations.
The only thing we did was the English one.
But even then, the community will help expand it,
because they're very passionate.
If you get a community to follow you,
Discord again is the key to that.
And Discourse, that forum I mentioned earlier.
Then these people will help you do this for free,
because they want their community to understand
the game in their own language.
We have some people who are very passionate, and they just want to translate.
And I'm happy to do that, so I can keep developing,
and localization will come pretty easy later.
So, if you're looking into multiplayer,
there are two major competitors.
You can use UNet, or you can use...
Oh, I think that's three.
UNet, Photon, or GameSparks.
Simply put, don't use U-Net.
U-Net was made by Unity, so your first bet will think, oh,
it's made by Unity, so it's probably the best.
Let me tell you, it's sort of an abandoned module.
We used it.
And there's no documentation.
There's no support.
And it's incomplete.
It's sort of like an alpha.
Maybe it will be good one day.
Maybe.
But for now, just simply skip it.
As for PlayFab.
PlayFab is the competitor to GameSparks.
They don't have real-time servers,
but they have the data sort of like GameSparks.
With PlayFab, there's tons of limitations.
And they may have been the example
we used earlier for the fine print.
So I recommend don't using them.
Again, I think GameSparks.
GameSparks and Photon are both great.
GameSparks does both, real-time and data.
Photon just does real-time.
But they both have really good documentation.
And you can make a multiplayer lobby in maybe two hours.
Really, it's fast, super fast.
So about our Kickstarter, our Kickstarter,
it's definitely a full-time job.
And if you think it won't be, you're in denial.
It's very hard work.
When you're on a Kickstarter, maybe years ago,
you could have concepts.
But now, it's not these days.
These days, you have to have almost a full game,
like maybe 75% complete.
You need to have full GIFs.
You need to have maybe 20 GIFs of the gameplay.
You need to have a gameplay trailer ready.
And you also need to have a monologue at the beginning.
Like you, yourself, preferably the owner,
is talking about the game.
Because on Kickstarter.
They're not buying the game, they're buying your concept.
They're investing in you, the developer.
So, it's very important.
Your speech comes before your trailer in a Kickstarter.
So you speak first.
You talk to the people.
Say, this is why you should invest in us.
And you need to be very passionate about it.
You need to show emotion.
uh... you know, even just explain like why
uh... how long you've been working on it and what it means to you. Why did you make this game?
Just really
pour your heart and soul into it.
And that's
what they're investing in.
We made a mistake earlier
at the very beginning.
We put the gameplay trailer first
and then our monologue.
And we had like a two minute trailer, it was sort of long.
And so once we swapped it, we put our speech first,
then suddenly you could actually see the curve go up,
like almost immediately.
Yeah, that's when we discovered people invest in you,
not the game, on Kickstarter.
And so for Kickstarter, if you're in Taiwan,
it's okay, you can still have a Kickstarter,
but you would need to have a partner
that has some sort of connection to US.
Because it needs to go to a US bank account.
And so if you have a friend or family or something like that,
just say you can give them a percentage.
Say, hey, if you help us with the Kickstarter,
we'll give you 10% just by being the agent for the bank
or something like that, too.
Let's see.
Oh, for trailer.
So I mentioned earlier, we had a two-minute trailer
at the beginning.
The trailer I showed you earlier was our newest one, and that's been the most successful one.
So that one's only 30 seconds long.
That means a 30-second trailer is significantly better than a 2-minute trailer.
This means it's cheaper to make, it's less stressful to make, and you may even be able to do it yourself.
I used Filmora to make that trailer.
I didn't hire anyone professional.
I think I paid maybe $50 for a license,
and I was able to put that together.
And the way I did it was, I just played a whole bunch of games,
and I kept recording them in full HD.
So over time, I have all these different clips.
And so if I want a specific event to happen,
I can just pull it and throw it in the trailer,
pull it and throw it in the trailer.
I only need 30 seconds, so it's not very stressful.
But if you really have no desire to make a game trailer,
you can hire someone.
Write down GameSharkStudio.
You can ask me later if you forget.
GameSharkStudio.
They're somewhere in Europe.
And they'll make you a really good trailer for really cheap,
like really good price.
We were very satisfied with them.
Oh, and one more thing about the trailer, because it is so important, your trailer.
Show the UI.
If you don't show the UI, even if it's gameplay, they won't believe you.
They'll think it's a cinematic trailer.
And so, yeah.
And so we're like, no, this is, I swear, this is gameplay.
Yeah, right, man.
So yeah, show your UI, and they'll believe you that it's gameplay.
And when you do have your trailer, start the gameplay instantly.
So, within the first two seconds.
Maybe show your... sort of like hours earlier, show your title for two seconds max.
Then go straight to the gameplay.
Oh, sorry, I mentioned this for the video makers.
It's Whale Shark Studio, not Game Shark Studio.
I think I was having a flashback to the old...
Gameshark days on Sega Genesis and Super Nintendo.
Okay, so
you can have your alpha on Steam.
Sorry, what is that 50% lower goal thing?
50% lower goal?
Oh, I'm sorry, I skipped a section. So for the Kickstarter,
50% lower goal, half lower goal.
That's what you want to aim for. So, in our case...
We asked for $20,000 because we wanted $20,000.
That was a mistake.
We were extremely stressed, because we only
got $21,000 in the end.
So we barely made it.
And if you know Kickstarter, it's all or nothing.
So it's better to ask for half.
As long as you can actually work with half,
as long as you can still make the game with half,
ask for half.
So if we did it again, we would have asked for $10,000.
So then once you hit $10,000, you say, oh, we're over the amount.
If we hit $20,000, we can say 200% funded.
It sounds so good, right?
I mean, the PR people will just eat that up.
It's just great.
And then you can have stretch goals.
So then everyone's excited.
They're trying to get that stretch goal.
Stretch goal is when you, if you make the funding,
if you're overfunded.
You could unlock special things in game.
And some of it, lots of the stretch goals,
you probably plan to do anyway.
But if you're funded, you can say you'll do it faster.
You'll do it like, you'll release it with this feature,
or maybe an extra class.
And so that really helps your funding.
So yeah, your alpha.
You can have your alpha on Steam,
and it doesn't have to be early access.
Early Access right now does not have a good vision.
When you see an Early Access game,
then people are skeptical.
They're suspicious.
They may not want to play it.
And if they do, they'll judge it as if it's a full release game.
So you may get negative reviews with AAA expectations
if they run into bugs.
And so.
What we did is we had a closed alpha and beta.
And when I say closed, I mean, you could buy keys from our website.
We use Stripe, by the way.
S-T-R-I-P-E
And so, at first we used Stripe, but if I did it again,
we would use itch.io
I-T-C-H dot I-O
They're free!
And you can just upload a bunch of keys,
and they'll buy it, and you can choose how much commission they get.
It's really easy.
pretty much free.
But the benefits are huge.
So let's say you submit your game to Steam.
Right now, you don't have to have it voted.
They changed it.
All you have to do is pay $100 US, and your game is on Steam.
It doesn't mean that it's launched yet.
As soon as you know that your game is going to be official,
then you do this, and you make a store.
So your store is going to have your gameplay trailer.
It's going to have screenshots.
And most importantly, it's going to have a coming soon.
You can say when the date is optional.
Coming soon, quarter four, 2018.
And most importantly, a wishlist button.
Add to wishlist.
This is huge.
You can have your game launch a year later if you wanted to.
And you have that store there.
Remember that I mentioned early marketing.
This is early marketing.
And people are adding to their wish list.
So when you do launch, every single person that added your
game to the wish list will be notified saying, hey, this
game has launched.
You should buy this game.
So that really helps.
So for example, I think I have our store page.
Let's see, store.
Oh wow, it's localized.
Oh, she changed it.
So when you have the store page, even if you're not live,
you can have it look exactly like something like this.
You can put a little graphic, say who's on the team.
This is really good for also if you're looking into investors
or team members.
If you're on the Steam store, you're official, right?
There's something about it that's
sort of prestigious about it.
And you just describe the game, and that's pretty much it.
Oh, and your specs.
Yeah, and then there's the Add to Wishlist button, which I
don't think shows on mine.
But it's somewhere here at the top.
And so when you have Steam, it's free marketing.
You may as well do it.
And also, it helps you for your release.
It makes your release really flowing.
Because in these days, people don't want to download a third-party application.
They don't want to download just an .exe file or something.
It looks sort of sketchy.
Maybe they'll think it's a virus, or maybe even your antivirus will pick it up as a virus.
Even if it's not, right?
So you want something that people can trust.
People trust Steam.
And so you can also use the API even before you're launched.
So you can have the login with Steam.
You can have Steam Friends.
You can have multiplayer servers.
We don't use their multiplayer servers,
but you can if you want to.
They have free multiplayer servers you can use.
And we didn't use that because we want to dedicate it.
So this one's peer-to-peer.
But I hear they're actually pretty decent.
Counter-Strike, of course, uses their own.
servers, and I think Borderlands also uses the Steam servers too.
Okay, so Discord is a really big part of our game, and I told you.
So we have the company server, which is private, and we have the public one.
Then what you want is you want community moderators.
And these guys don't just moderate your community.
They're almost like lower level developers.
They're probably going to end up being more knowledgeable
about your own game than you.
Because lots of times, you're more often developing your game
rather than playing it.
And so someone once said that if you like video games,
don't make video games.
Because you won't be able to play as much.
Anyway, Discord you can do so much.
It's sort of like Slack if you've never used it before.
But, for video games.
But it's even more than that.
I mean, I would use it even for not video games.
You can program bots to do anything.
There's a really good API called Discord.js.
You can use that for free.
And, for example, we use it for in-game engagement and moderation.
So what we can do is,
we can type in a bot command.
to suspend a player in-game, or to warn them, or to grant them gold.
Let's say that someone translates your game for you.
I can type in, like, exclamation mark, grant gold, and boom.
And then it grants this user gold in-game,
even though I'm typing it from Discord.
So you can think, oh, and also Discord just recently added rich presents.
This is sort of like Steam, how they know what you're doing.
Steam will say, he's playing Throne of Lies.
And Discord goes even deeper.
Discord will say, he's playing Throne of Lies,
and he's on day two in game.
Or his game is just finishing, or something like that.
And sort of like Steam, there's even a Join button,
or a Spectate button you can use.
So there's a lot of stuff you can do.
people go crazy about titles and praise and stuff like recognition
because in our discord we have twelve thousand players
and it's really hard to stand out when there's
you know we have an average of
two thousand players online at the same time
so the list is just
it's just a dump of players
and so what ends up happening is
people want to stand out and so when they do
when they contribute to the wikia
or they report bugs
you can have a bugs section, a bugs channel, a feedback channel
if the
if they help new players a lot.
You can grant them titles to make them stand out.
And this really boosts morale, like crazy.
And for any of you that play online games,
if you attend like a GM event or something,
and you get an exclusive title, it's so cool, isn't it?
It's the same thing in Discord.
Players feel cool about it, and it
makes them want to engage even more in the community.
And what you can do, too, as game developers,
you can have an official game server.
So you can see our URL is actually discord.gg slash tol.
And so that's because we're an official game server.
It didn't take much to do it.
All we did is fill out an application and say, hey,
we're the real developers.
And this is the game that we're supporting.
And so suddenly you get an official verification.
You get the URL there.
And then when people join it, you
can actually get a
Let's see, discord.tv slash tol.
You can actually get some splash art, and it makes it look super cool.
It looks very official.
So, uh, oh, there it is.
So it looks sort of like this.
And you can customize the art in the background.
So, when you make your games, a lot of people are going to request game keys.
They're going to say, I'm press.
I'm a famous.
and they'll say, I have millions of views, trust me.
And they're going to ask for keys.
So, what you do is, you say, hey, come to Discord,
link your Twitch account, link your Twitter account,
or you can even, they can also support Steam, link your Steam account,
and we'll give you keys. You'll find very fast
that half the people never come to Discord because they're fake.
So, more than half, I'd say about 75% of the people that ask for keys are fake.
So, Discord, because you can link your accounts, this has been an invaluable tool to verify people, to see if they're real or not.
And ever since then, we haven't seen any keys on, you know, Kinguin and G2A.
Speaking of which...
If your game does end up on Kinguin or G2A without your permission,
you can send them a message, like an official message,
say, hey, please take it down and blacklist,
and then make sure you speak to the manager.
We did that, and they made sure that they won't show our game on Kinguin or G2A ever again.
I'm sure this helps some of you guys out there.
You know what I'm talking about.
So in your Discord, you also want to have, I mentioned earlier, a feedback and bugs section.
Just have it, just have them dump it there.
You can have some bot commands for FAQs,
like how to get your logs to post it in the bug reports,
how, uh, FAQ for, like, uh, your links,
or, you know, anything complex that you say over and over.
You can have it all bot commands.
And so, it's sort of like if you ever watched a Twitch streamer,
you know, you can type ! and a command, and lots of times it'll give them links or information.
You can do something like that.
And then news have a read-only section for players to see.
You can tag everyone, so that even if they're offline,
they'll eventually see it.
Let's go to the next slide here.
So let's talk about Unity.
Why Unity?
Well, Unity is free while developing.
That's always an incentive for indie devs.
They have an asset store that's invaluable.
The asset store, I'm sure that you've all experienced it if you've used Unity before.
They have tons of free assets, or almost free assets.
Don't forget that your game doesn't have to start with the final assets.
You saw my blooper video at the very beginning.
Our game models don't look like that, the textures don't look like that, neither do the shadings.
But it really allowed us to get started fast.
To just throw something in there instead of just squares.
you could have just squares, but it's sort of good for morale, and it's good for screenshots.
And especially if you're doing a Kickstarter, or you're trying to get some press,
if you show someone with some type of model, or environment, or art, or some sort of placeholders,
it's better than just squares, and black and white.
And that pretty much is the definition of prototyping.
It's just having a bunch of placeholders
so that people can envision what your game will
be when you're finished.
It doesn't necessarily have to work all the way,
but give them something to think about.
Unity is high level.
This means that unlike Unreal, you
don't have to program memory management.
You don't have to program low level physics.
it'll probably be more efficient if you do.
I mean, it will be more efficient if you do.
But the fact that you can
just skip all this stuff
and just go straight to making the game
is really good for morale.
It's good for prototyping.
And...
you can always do the optimization stuff later.
Right?
I mean, lots of times when you're making a game,
you don't want to...
you want to start with the game itself, not all the lower level stuff.
You can make games faster.
It's faster to learn, too.
and they have good tutorials.
If you don't know something, just Google it again.
Watch YouTube video.
Unity actually has built in, they
have their own native tutorial videos.
And they're very high budget tutorials.
They have videos.
They have demos.
They have full games that they can give you to poke around
with, depending on your learning style.
Some people like to reverse engineer things.
You can do multiple ports.
Nintendo Switch has been really big lately for Indie developers.
And so you can port it straight to Nintendo Switch
with almost effortlessly.
Or at the beginning, we were just going to do Windows.
And then we realized how easy it was to do Mac and Linux, too.
So we're just like, OK, all it requires us is to switch to Mac,
build, done.
So if you can, you may as well.
And so, especially if your game is very console-friendly,
for consoles, you may require some extra stuff,
like for the controller support.
You want buttons to go to different buttons.
But in the long term, it's not that much
to be able to port it to consoles, too.
And now, why not Unity?
So Unity, they don't make games unlike Unreal.
Unreal.
makes AAA games that people want to play.
This means that they're developers too.
I mean, when I say they, I mean like the big guys,
the CEOs and stuff.
And so these guys actually are developers.
And so if they run into a bug while they're
making a AAA game, like Unreal Tournament or something,
then they will go in and they'll fix it.
But as for Unity, they outsource all their demos.
And so if they run into a bug.
then they don't really fix it for a few years.
And so there are countless unfixed bugs.
In our examples, in our experience, we have freezes,
we have crashes, we have UI bugs.
If you've ever used the scroller in Unity,
it'll always shift everything over to the side,
and your screen will sometimes turn pink.
And it's just not fun.
But if you experience bugs, because Unity is so modular,
you can just work around it.
Go to the Unity store and find an alternative.
You don't have to use the Unity built-in stuff.
You don't like the scroller?
Go in and find a scroller, or you can make your own.
They make it really easy to be modular in a very simple way.
I made my own scroller in the end,
and it ended up not being, it didn't take me very long
to make, and then I used the template from the Asset Store
to help me get there.
So yeah, you will experience bugs, but you can just skip it.
But be sure that the upgrades are not stable,
so be sure you copy your entire project,
and then try upgrading if you're ever trying to upgrade.
That's the only way to be safe.
OK, so they're free.
They're free, actually.
While you're developing, it's free.
Even when you launch, it's still free.
But if you do the personal edition,
they'll sort of shame you.
They'll put the personal logo at the bottom.
So it makes you really unprofessional.
I've seen people give negative reviews just saying, oh,
developers are cheap because they have the personal edition
or something.
So that's something really to think about, really.
And so if you make over $100,000 or you
don't want that personal edition slash screen to show,
then you can pay for the licenses.
You don't have to jump to the pro license.
They have a per seat license, but they have a lower level one that's like $35 per month
per seat or something like that, if you make under a certain amount of money.
So it's not bad. It's really not.
And then lastly, Unity does abandon modules. Think of Unreal more like a game engine and
Unity more like a sales engine. So lots of times they really push marketing
very hard.
so they want to add, they want to get the feature list really high.
And so that's wonderful, I love features, but not at the cost of stability.
And, you know, I don't want them, I want them to continuously develop it.
And in this case, I mentioned U-Net earlier, I said don't use U-Net.
And then they also have a service called Collab, Collaborate.
It's very unstable too, it's like Gits.
Just use Git and GitLab, guys.
In the end, we got rid of all of our Unity services,
and suddenly our game editor is way faster and way less buggy.
So really quickly, what I plan for the future.
We have a private API, and that API is so that it'll spread out to other services and stuff, like Discord.
We want a public one, so that people can make community sites without involving us.
They can have stats sites and stuff, whatever they can come up with.
We want to improve our UI and UX experience.
We want to have a better community engagement, so we want to make a Twitch extension, for example, so that players can click.
And we have different abilities.
We want them to be able to hover over the abilities
to see what they do.
We want them to be able to click on a journal
and it opens a journal with their last known entry.
There's some fun stuff you can do with that.
And because hardly any indie games do this, if you do that,
you will be on Twitch.
Because audience engagement is a very rare thing in Twitch.
And streamers have to work really hard for it.
So if you can give them something,
then they're more likely to play your game.
And that's why we want it really bad.
As for publishers, people always ask,
do we need a publisher?
I would say that if you're doing PC, Mac, and Linux,
I would say no, you don't need a publisher.
Except if you're going to China.
Because they have all these rules.
They have tons of rules.
And you want to get on Tencent.
And especially since we're in Taiwan,
then you know how that goes.
They need to approve everything and make sure that.
Yeah, you want a publisher to do that.
And also, your art assets may even be localized, too.
So it's not just about translating it
to the local language.
It's art.
It's community.
Even the website will look different.
It's localized.
You want everything a little bit tailored
towards that specific demographic.
But yeah, I hear that if you do a mobile game,
almost every person I hear says.
If you're doing a mobile game, you do want a publisher.
Because there are so many mobile games out there,
the publishers will help you stand out.
We want a physical card game.
So if you're making games, then you may as well
branch out as much as you can.
And so we have this game concept.
And we realized it would make a wonderful physical card game.
And so we don't even have to make it.
We just have to find a partner that's
very good at making these types of games
and say, hey, we have the concept.
And you can build this.
Let's work together.
And so that's, you branch it out as much as possible.
And then we eventually want to keep going with new games,
although we want to keep updating our current one.
So if you guys have any questions beyond this,
let's say we have some questions and answers,
and then later on you go, ah, I forgot to ask.
Just go on Discord and ask me.
I'm i42xblade, the link there.
If you go to that link on the right,
throneofli.es slash blah.
This has everything we talked about tonight.
It has this PowerPoint presentation in PDF form.
And it has some of these links.
Yeah, so if you're just remembering something,
just remember throneofli.es slash blah.
It has everything.
So, do you guys have any questions for me?
Sorry, so I think we already run the flower.
Oh, OK.
So I think we could take a short, very short break.
OK, sure.
And we'll come back for the Q&A session, like four or five.