好,那我們最開始先請今天的團人先跟各位介紹一下他們自己
And I've been here for maybe 4 or 5 years.
I'm originally from California.
I studied in Hawaii.
So I've internalized the online game of Deceit,
which is an online multiplayer game.
And pretty much you have a bunch of good guys together,
and there's bad guys among you.
You have to find them, kill them.
That's how you do it.
And other than that, yeah.
OK.
Yeah, that's it.
OK, we'll get back to you.
We have more questions than that.
Hey, I'm Jonas.
I'm a programmer.
I was working on Subnautica, underwater adventure
game for PC and consoles.
A colleague of mine is here right now.
He's also a programmer.
I also live in Taiwan, I've been here for a year, a little bit over a year now.
It's really nice.
Our current project, I mean Subnautica came out a year ago,
and our current project is a follow-up game called Subnautica Below Zero.
It's very similar to the first one.
It's a separate game, it's not DLC, right?
It's a...
We think of it as a stand-alone expansion, because we don't want to call it Subnautica 2.
It's more like Subnautica 1.5 or something.
But yeah, it is not a DLC.
And I'm originally from Germany.
Hello, I'm Fernando. I've been in Taiwan for three years now.
I'm working on a multiplayer...
And I'm originally from the United States,
but grew up in Germany, actually.
And yeah, I went to school at the University of Texas,
Austin, computer science as sort of my technical background.
And I've been working on this game for quite a while.
But it's not out yet.
Soon, though.
How long?
How long can you go?
At least six years.
I think it's getting closer to seven maybe,
I'll have to calculate it.
But yeah, a long time.
All the time you have been in Taiwan, right?
Three and a half years of it in Taiwan.
We came here for half a year, left, and came back.
So most of it in Taiwan, actually.
Okay.
Nice.
Since Ed isn't here yet, there is another...
We have another speaker.
He's probably just...
Is it on?
Yeah, I think it's on.
Sorry.
It ducks in and out.
Yeah.
那我們還有一位就是語壇人
那就是等他來的時候我們再請他來致接
那所以我下一個問題想要請教他們的是
就是說因為他們都有各自不同的背景
那想說就是也是來台灣也是一段時間
那他們自己在原本的國家或是社群
他們在那邊看到的跟在這邊看到的有什麼不一樣
So my next question is, what was your expectation of the game development scene in Taiwan before and after you came here?
Before you actually thought of doing a long stay or trying to settle down in Taiwan, did you expect there is a game development scene that you want to participate in?
And what are your expectations of the game development scene in Taiwan?
was and did that change after you actually set it up here?
And also like, maybe we can talk about the differences that you see from other parts of the world.
You can start.
Ed just arrived.
Oh yeah, okay.
Just in time for it.
Sorry, sorry.
Yay!
Definitely never been here before.
Now Ed has been here like for many times.
Yeah, but is it... yeah, please.
Hi, I'm Ed. I'm a game developer. I just moved here.
I'm making a Japanese-style RPG.
And doing contract stuff as well, so...
Bye.
Okay. Nice. Yeah, we'll get back to you.
So, it's all about... how about you start with...
I didn't have much of an idea, really no idea what the dev scene would be like in Taiwan.
The only dev scene I really know, and honestly I don't know it that well because I've always been a bit of a hermit,
I think I know the Taiwan better was back in Austin, Texas.
I assumed that there was one, and Taiwan's a big country, and Taipei's the capital.
But until my wife sort of got me to leave...
I had no clue what it was like.
Now, to compare the two, though, I was pleasantly surprised.
I think that I feel more comfortable in the Taiwan
dev scene than I did in Austin.
I love Austin, so if anybody here is back home, I love it.
I was there since 96, so I have a lot of roots there.
But I think
and I felt everybody really approachable here.
You know, I have a big handicap that I don't speak Mandarin pretty much at all,
but without Amanda translating for me.
But a lot of people speak English, and even when people didn't speak English,
you know, they really went out of their way to talk to me and to connect.
So my experience has been really great, actually.
And I've been a lot, you know, every month.
you know, since I work from home, I think a lot of us, probably not all of us,
you know, it's every time there's some indie meetup,
you know, every month I always make sure I go there because
it really helps a lot,
even if you have communication barriers, just to be with other people who are going through what you're going through and to talk about, and also
before that, the only real socialization that I did was through
Discord, so it's been a big help.
And actually my game has...
I've gotten a lot of good ideas from talking to people here in Taiwan.
So it's been really great. So I'm really happy to be a part of the community.
So what was...
Do you know even, or any game that you think is from Taiwan before you came here?
Before I came here?
Honestly, no. I know it all.
But no, I did not...
Maybe some game that I played was from here and I didn't realize it was from Taiwan.
A lot of times it's...
It's easy to remember the game, but hard to remember who the developer was,
and let alone where they're from.
But no, I didn't.
Oh, okay. Got it.
So, how about Jonas?
That's difficult to follow up, but Richard.
So, before I came here,
I was working from home and trying.
for about four years.
And I've lived in a lot of different countries.
And unfortunately,
I haven't been able to connect with any indie scene
in any other country, but here it was very, very easy.
The only other indie scene...
I think that situation is in Germany too.
People think if you're a programmer, you should do business and programs.
Yes, yes, absolutely.
We have a very startup, unfriendly culture in Germany.
It's very, very difficult to create a company.
It needs a lot of money and lawyers and all that stuff.
And then once you have a company, and you hire someone,
it's very, very difficult to fire that person.
And you have to pay them a lot of money.
And so it's like if you have any kind of risk in your startup,
and that's what startups are about,
then Germany is a terrible place.
And we also have laws that we just don't accept certain jobs.
You simply cannot be that job because it's not
on the list of acceptable jobs to be.
So in Germany, we really only have.
like one, we used to have one big game studio,
which was Crytek, they are doing Far Cry,
you might have heard of that,
but I'm not sure if they are around anymore,
or if they closed down.
And then we had a few, like,
web game developers, right?
And maybe they transitioned now to mobile,
but we never really had a proper, like,
computer game or console game industry at all.
Which is really weird.
Maybe Germans are too practical?
I think they are just too locked up in old ways.
Okay.
Like new things are not good in Europe.
We have a different kind of thinking.
I have a follow up with that though.
Gamescon is in Germany.
Yes, exactly.
The biggest games convention in the world.
Yeah, in the world.
is in Germany, right? And board games are super huge in Germany.
Oh, Euro games. Euro games, yeah.
You've probably played the Settlers of Catan, right?
That's a German game.
And actually, most of these style of games are from Germany.
there is like an indie board game scene, I guess?
Or, I'm not sure if they are indie, because it's just,
it's literally just five guys,
and it's always the same five guys,
and they make all the games.
And, and, but yeah, for computer games,
it's, it's just terrible.
Wow.
There's one really big one.
Interesting one.
In space, the X series,
and they kind of kept space games alive.
Oh, so.
ErgoSoft, is an,
Oh, right, right, right.
It's a big company.
So there's one funny thing going on in parts of like,
in Europe, so Germany is a little bit part of that,
which is like, in Sweden they make these deep,
like simulator type of games, right?
Like all the, what's the publisher of Pandora, no?
Paradox.
Paradox, yeah, Paradox Interactive, right?
And they make a certain type of game that is like,
And so there are some niches of games that we do make in Europe.
This, right? X. X series.
I think maybe also Farm Simulator? I think that's also...
Farm Simulator is actually from Switzerland.
Oh, that's from Switzerland. Okay. Well, that's awesome.
And they are doing quite well, right?
And then there's, I think, Euro Truck Simulator.
And I'm not sure if that comes from Poland or something.
Factorio comes from Poland.
Or Czech...
Czech, Czech. I think.
So, it's basically, Germany is sitting in the middle of Europe, and France is doing well, and Poland is doing well, and Sweden is doing well, and Switzerland is doing well, and they are all making games.
And we don't, but we sit in the middle, so Gamescom is where we are.
But they all come to your country, for Gamescom.
And of course it's a big market, right?
The point that I'm trying to make is once I came here, Subnautica just came out and
I was like, okay, I should probably take what I learned in Subnautica and go to my conferences
and talk a little bit about that.
And I Googled and I found, the first thing I found was TGF.
So I have no idea what that is.
I wrote an email, I submitted my talk.
TGF was my first talk conference, and after that I was in lots of other conferences,
none of them was as good as TGF.
You got something really good here, treasure it.
I should stop talking.
So, I've lived in Taiwan for a few years now, and before I came up here,
I didn't really think about making a game specifically for the...
I just thought, everyone's just doing mobile these days.
And over time, I realized that although it is a large market,
I was also very wrong.
There's still a lot of people that do PC.
You have the gaming centers all over the place.
And I had one, by the way.
And I made the first one in South Carolina a long time ago.
So I'm very interested in these.
And people don't go there and they play mobile games together.
They play PC games.
And so, yeah, the market's still very big.
Big here, and especially in not just Taiwan, but China, too.
You see Tencent that has 250 million people in one locale,
which is pretty wild compared to Steam that has a scattered
locale of 125 million.
And so, yeah, the scene is pretty big here,
all over this place.
And anyway, in
Taiwan, we recently started translating our game to traditional Chinese.
And this was only recently, because some people from Taiwan started playing our game.
We saw them streaming on Twitch, and we see this and we suddenly notice that these people are playing our game.
It's completely in English. They're talking in Chinese.
They have this whole, like, their own custom-made wiki that they made with just all the translations and stuff.
And it's good.
You know, Taiwanese people are very passionate about this stuff.
And we started translating, and we're collaborating with some of these people.
And everyone's just so nice.
And they just want the game in Chinese, and they're even happy to play it while it's still in English.
So that really surprised me.
So yeah, that's where we are at right now, is we want to get the game out for Eastern culture.
and spread the word.
I think one point you bring up is that
a lot of people speak in Mandarin or Chinese
on the Throne of Light servers.
I think maybe one aspect of that is that
we have a lot of board game players
and board game
developers here too.
And like, werewolf kind of game
is...
like originally from those, right?
Yeah, the werewolf mafia genre itself was originally in,
came from Russia, is the farthest back in my research
that I could find.
And so from Russia, it went to the east.
And so what's funny about my game is that in Europe and...
United States, Australia, I have to really deeply explain what my game is, because it's
a tabletop game in disguise, and this genre is still very niche in this locale.
But in the eastern locale, it's not niche at all, and I had no idea.
Apparently there's some games that have millions of downloads of this genre.
I just need to tell people one sentence about the game, and they go, oh I know that genre,
I know that genre.
How is that even possible?
And so I was very shocked and of course pleased to hear this.
And so as soon as I learned about this stuff,
I should have researched it earlier.
But yeah, we're trying to get it out there.
Okay, nice.
And...
Maybe next, like, Ed can follow up with
like, what was your expectations about Taiwan
or the game scene here before you came here
after you came here?
What were you doing back in UK?
Things like that.
So when I was in the UK I used to work for a studio
called Mediasonic
who make a bunch of mobile stuff and console stuff.
I was a server engineer there so I built
server side systems for multiplayer games and things.
Then I met my now wife who is Taiwanese and I came to visit her.
I think that was maybe...
Like two years ago?
That was three years ago.
Did I come to...
here then?
I don't think I did. I think I was way too...
Anyway, um...
So I used up all my holiday seeing her and then two...
see her again like less than a year later and have to wait for my vacation time from
work. I quit my job to work, like spend my savings working full time on my then hobby
project which is Jack Move, my Japanese style RPG.
And then I kept coming back here for longer stretches.
And then came here, met Johnson and stuff.
I think my expectation before I came was that there wasn't much of an indie scene.
And that's purely because I had a friend who worked in games, who lived in Taiwan.
maybe four or five years ago, and then he left because I don't think I've seen him at that time.
I don't know, were there that many game developers maybe?
That's the impression I got from him anyway.
I think maybe the difficulty lies in the fact that it's hard for foreign game developers to get connected to the locals at first.
Yeah, maybe.
We really didn't reach out to the game developers who are living in Taiwan right now, maybe since just a few years ago.
He worked at a studio.
In studio, I think it tends to be a very closed environment for big companies in Taiwan.
I think that's the same in a lot of places as well.
In my hometown, that's why.
There's loads of indie developers. I come from Brighton in the UK.
There's a lot of bigger studios.
I used to run an indie meetup there.
All the indie developers would come, but people from the bigger studios would just stick to themselves.
They wouldn't really socialise outside of their company.
I know UK has a pretty big indie scene too, right?
Yes.
And Austin too.
I forgot to ask, is there any game developers in Hawaii though?
Game developers? Yay!
Game developers in Hawaii?
When I lived in Hawaii, I was mostly doing things for games instead of making my own games.
So I would do everything...
surrounding actual game development.
So I used to do
stuff for Cyber Cafe Software and such.
So I'm sort of unfamiliar, but
I was very interested in eventually making a game, so I did keep my eye out,
and I did not see
a single game developer during my stay. I was there for
years.
I think the indie developer scene in Hawaii is
pretty small.
I was just interested in what's the situation in every...
from all your...
where you came from, basically.
So...I guess next...
starting from the next questions, we are going to talk a little bit more about
the actual game development challenges that
maybe you faced before, things like that.
我接下來會想要問的問題
就是我們有列舉的問題
那其中其實有一個會跟
其實蠻多獨立開發者都會遇到一樣的狀況
就是說譬如你是一個剛開始做第一款遊戲的開發者
那你要怎麼樣去找到你的第一個玩家族群
或者是說你已經找到一個
你覺得你已經找到一個市場
可是你要怎麼樣用有限人力去跟這些人互動之類的
I think this is what I want to ask next.
Because they have a lot of games in their games,
and there are many types of games.
And I think most of you utilize Discord right now,
because I think Discord is a very great platform.
And I think we can have a comparison between you guys.
What did you do, and what you didn't do,
and this is how I do it.
This kind of thing.
So I guess maybe we can start from Jonas.
Sure.
What we didn't do was spend any money.
So we've been around for a very long time, like 15 years or something.
I mean the studio that I'm working for, right?
And we tend to take a long time to make a single game.
And the way we work is we try to put as many information about what we are doing out there.
Like we put our daily task board, like we use travel to do task tracking, we put that public.
And we...
play them on Steam, right?
So we make our check-in messages publicly.
They go to Twitter.
And by just being very open as a studio,
we give lots of people the opportunity
to create something around what we were doing,
like make entertainment out of our process of making a game.
So we are seeing lots of people from the community.
writing the wiki for us, or translating the game for us, or doing tech support for us
on the forums if someone has a problem.
Or if someone comes and is not happy, they help that person maybe solve that problem.
So we have a really...
big and very helpful, friendly community.
And I think the reason why we do have that
is because we are so transparent and open about everything
we do.
And we have a really good community manager guy
who keeps it very positive.
So I'll summarize this in Mandarin.
他們的公司Unknown World Entertainment
其實之前做過Natural Selection系列
然後其實那個就已經是好多年前的作品
然後後來才又用
大概用同樣的開發方式
他們其實有之前在GDC有講過
就他們的算是製作人有在GDC講過一個
叫做Open Development的演講
那就是那個時候是在講Natural Selection 2
那後來他們也出了Subnautica
跟現在是出Below Zero這樣
那我接下來比較好奇的是
就是他們當初最早
因為其實最...
我覺得比較重要的是
你一開始怎麼知道
你要去engage某一群人
這樣子的面向
因為我想說如果你已經有一個
蠻大的玩家支持者群的話
其實理論上你後續要做什麼事情
是相對簡單一些
所以我想我接下來的問題是
你怎麼...
like first engaged, you know, the first group of people,
you know, maybe they play Natural Selection 1
as a mod of Half-Life,
but they play Natural Selection 2.
Like, did that community build up
and carry over to the next game?
Right, right, right.
That's a good question.
So, the very first game you just mentioned
is Natural Selection 1,
which was a free mod for Half-Life.
That was a competitive,
aliens vs. marines kind of shooter.
And then,
That mod was so popular that the people who made it
decided to start a company and make that mod
as a standalone product.
And that was called Natural Selection 2.
It was basically the same, but now as a standalone product
and for money.
And I'm sure that a good amount of the community that
played the first game came in and then bought the second game.
However, what we put in.
happen again. We had a big community from Natural Selection 2, they were not interested
in Subnautica at all. And it kind of makes sense because Natural Selection is a competitive
multiplayer shooter, Subnautica is a single player adventure diving game. There's very
little overlap in taste. So only super fans of our studio itself came over, but those
are very, very rare.
And that took a long, long time.
When we launched...
How long was it you were in Early Access?
It was in Early Access three years.
Three years for Early Access?
Yes.
And the launch on Early Access was terrible.
We wanted to have, I think, between 10,000 or 10,000 to 50,000 sales.
That was our Early Access launch goal.
I don't think we had hit 10,000.
And then three years later, we sold a total of like 2 million.
So our early access launch compared to our final release,
like all the sales that we made in between,
was totally nothing.
And the community built up over time very, very slowly.
So the big surge of sales is basically very close
to the access.
Every single month, 5,000 people buy the game.
Okay.
Basically.
And it just keeps going and going.
There's no end in sight.
Oh.
So you don't see like, maybe they are like stopping or like long tail right now.
It's just a very steady...
It's very, very steady, yeah.
Because we were...
We were releasing an update...
new cool feature in it.
And so what happens every time we make an update,
we see a spike in our sales, and then there's
the tail starting.
And then next month is spike and tail, and spike and tail.
And because our update frequency is so high,
it never really goes totally down.
It keeps at a pretty consistent level.
I see.
Dylan, can you also say something about this?
For throwing it, are you talking about the sales curve right now?
In regards to the sales curve...
How did you start? I know you actually talked about this...
Oh, in the last time?
Yeah, last time, but you can briefly talk about that again.
I've learned some new things.
everything we funnel to Discord.
And we have a ramen noodles budget,
and so what can you do except to bring it into Discord?
And so when Discord came out, I was one of the first
to realize that, oh man, this is like the ideal platform.
It has everything.
It has voice, chat, permissions.
We use it for both community and dev collaboration, too.
It's just a beautiful platform.
And so everything that you do, every announcement you make,
every landing page that you have.
you funnel it to Discord.
And so you don't want to list all of your links, which
some people do.
Lots of times, you just want to put one or two links.
So maybe the link to your game and the link to your Discord.
And in your Discord, that's where
you can have your whole list of things.
Because they're in your Discord.
They're where you want them.
So then make sure it's funneled there.
And make sure that your welcome page in Discord,
like where your invite link goes to.
make sure it has a whole bunch of the most important things
you want them to do.
Don't just throw them in general chat.
They'll get overwhelmed.
And they won't see what you want them to see.
And most of the time, it's the important links,
and it's the little social sites or extras.
You want to point them to news.
So what we do is we like to use discord.js API.
And we run it on our Node server.
And it's just self-hosted.
We use DigitalOcean.
And it's really easy to set up.
They have good documentation.
And so we use our bot very often for engagement.
And so we actually use Discord with in-game integration
as well.
And so in-game, we'll try to pull people into Discord, too.
It'll show how many people are there.
There'll be a Discord button.
In beta, we didn't have enough players.
It takes 16 players to make a game.
And so in alpha, beta, we were lucky to get eight,
which is our minimum.
And so what we would do is we'd use our bot to announce.
So whenever someone queued up for the game,
you can imagine that there's only maybe five to 15 people
on at a time back then.
And so then it would ping Discord.
You could join a roll and be pingable whenever someone
is together in matchmaking.
And so after that, the bot would say, hey guys, everyone,
join up, join up.
Join this rank to be pinged for the future.
And so it would show a little embed.
It'd show how many players are there.
And as the players go up to the minimum,
it would start hyping people up.
And so it'd use little Unicode emojis and read,
oh, it's there, just one more.
And so it'd actually have a link where.
You can make a Steam link.
I forgot how it is offhand, but you can Google it.
You can make it a link, so it'll launch your application
via your app ID.
And so that was really useful, too.
So you just click it, and if it's installed,
it will launch the game.
And another thing we did later on is we made it so that it
would go to a special link where it would detect if you
have Steam running.
If so, it would launch the game.
And if not, it would bring you to the store page.
So it was a really useful bot, which eventually got really annoying later
once we got tons of people and we were out of beta.
So we had to kill that feature off, but it's still dormant.
Anything you can do to engage.
We have an overwhelming amount of channels,
which we keep trying to shorten it,
but we realize they all serve its purpose once you have a certain amount of people.
So eventually what we do is we have achievement section.
We don't have time for Steam achievements yet.
It's a planned feature.
But if you're going to do it, you've got to do it right.
You've got to have hundreds.
And you've got to have your stat system perfectly set up.
So what we can do is the lazy way, I mean the temporary way,
is to make an achievements channel in Discord.
And so we say, hey, if you have 500 hours played,
we'll give you a special colored roll.
If you have 1,000 hours played, we'll
give you a shinier roll.
And we just have...
Can the score know that information through the API too?
No.
This one we actually do manually, but it's not bad.
And we just say you have to have a, you know, we just verify it through a public profile.
And if they're not public profile, you know, we can, we say that you can either...
Take a screenshot or something.
You can, well, not screenshot, but we say that you either have to set it public so we
can see that you have 500 hours or you can link to your review.
So one or the other will work.
We prioritized the first one to make sure
that we're not biased for reviews.
So that seems to be working pretty well.
What else for engagement?
We have a feedback and bugs channel.
This is really good.
We set up the bot so that any time somebody posts there,
we have a cool down to make sure you don't spam it.
Then the bot will put a thumbs up, thumbs down.
And all the other emojis we have disabled.
And so people can vote on these ideas and bugs.
If they've experienced it, they can thumbs up.
And over time, you realize that some people will spam thumbs
down on people.
So we made it Facebook-like, where it's only thumbs up.
But if you want to, if you can handle the feedback, you can
type in hashtag.
debate. And if you do that, then the thumbs down will show.
Yeah, so that seems to be working really well.
So that way, if they truly want negative and positive unbiased feedback,
that works really well. And that's been really awesome, because
you can't implement every feature. You want to, but it's impossible.
So you want to go with people where it might seem like a good idea, but
maybe only you think it's a good idea, and maybe only they think it's a good idea,
and no one else likes the idea.
So the emoji thumbs up, down count really
assists on this matter.
Yeah, and Discord.
What you can do as well is, if you're not an official game
yet, make a memorable short URL.
It's really easy to set a short URL service.
Like ours is t-o-l-i-dot-e-s.
So you can just do something really short.
And you have to be partnered so that it can.
Am I right?
For the official one, yeah, you do have to be partnered.
So our partner link is discord.gg slash T-O-L.
But in the early days, I had my own short URL service,
sort of like Bitly or Google's old one that they just
continue.
OK, yeah.
You can make your own, and then just put slash discord.
So that way, everyone remembers it.
Because you want people to always remember easily
where it is and where.
你希望所有人都能夠加入,讓他們可以告訴朋友們
他們知道Link by Heart,是一個很容易記得的東西
你不希望他們需要去看,因為如果他們被迷惑一分鐘
那個人就永遠不會加入
明白,OK
那問一下現場有多少人的Discord是已經有
就是像用這種工具去做遊戲聯動
還沒有啊
你可以先問一下
有人是做Multiplayer遊戲的嗎
就是會需要譬如說要揪團的
還是說要開台的那種
Fernando
OK
一個
所以我猜Fernando可以跟Dylan一起說
因為我覺得你們兩個
在開始的時候
就像是在Alpha版本的時候
你需要
paying people in channel, this kind of thing,
to actually get people to join your game.
Yeah, so maybe, like...
So I'll talk about how my experience has been with Discord,
what I've done to...
Or maybe how you've been playing games.
How you did in the early days, what you did to get players.
I'm still, I mean, I assume my community's probably a lot smaller.
I know it's a lot smaller, Subnautica's like 37,000 or something.
And, uh, game...
I think it's 15,000.
It just grew here. Another 5,000 at least while we were here.
And thrown at lies, how big is your community? 14,000.
14,000. I'm just a tiny little 280.
But my experience, so I started six years ago.
When I started, of course, Discord didn't exist.
And at the very beginning it was just friends.
Getting over to my house, sitting on the sofa, on the computer.
And we'd just get together on wireless keyboards, gamepads,
and play all over the local LAN.
Eventually, after many times my number one, Gerald,
who's still with me, a very good friend of mine
who's been playing since day one, he said, get this out there.
He was like, release it, launch it, launch it, release it.
And so he encouraged me.
I did a teaser trailer a couple years ago.
I set up a website, set up forums, sent out emails.
and crickets chirping.
I think I was very fortunate that Joystick, it was literally
like the day before they closed that website,
they covered my video.
And I got a lot of people viewing it from there.
Mainly a lot of people being puzzled.
But you should look up the old video,
because it looks nothing like what it looks like right now.
Can I just type Joystick?
Joystick is closed.
uh...
but you can type
this one right here
yeah if you go to youtube
and type
hunter neck going to the trailers
you'll see the old trailer
uh... but uh...
but anyways
so that got you know
it went from like nothing to several thousand views
uh...
which one?
just type like
hunter neck going to the trailers
So there's the real one.
Yeah, that one.
Somebody copied it.
Yeah.
So this one was the real one.
GameTrailer's also covered it, but the one with thousands
of views is a different one.
But that'll show you the video.
But anyways, my goal was to get people to play the game.
I did a Twitch stream and everything.
And I went and posted it in different forums.
If you skip a little bit forward, you'll see.
You can see it.
Yeah.
That's the video right there.
Yeah, and I set up that website. So what did that accomplish?
I got some weird, you know, interesting feedbacks and...
This is nothing like the game right now.
No, nothing, nothing.
This is completely different from the game now.
There's a baby.
What is that?
It's going in.
It's disco balls.
Yeah.
This is actually a funny video because these guys that work for one of the big sites, I
don't know who it was that did a series, and they did Halo and they did some other big
games besides mine.
But anyways, and then I went, for the teaser, basically those are players spawning.
All those things you're seeing from the sky, and it's a server spawning 700 players all
in one instance.
Yeah, it's a street crawl. 7 times what Fortnite does, you know, 6 years ago.
With crazy physics and portals to different areas and all sorts of crazy...
You can climb like Spider-Man, swing like the Titanfall, yeah, a lot of stuff.
That's a swing.
I realized I haven't showed your game on screen right now, I should show that.
Yeah, you can look at it.
And I mentioned bigger battles than any MMOFPS, so I got a lot of fans of Planetside, too.
Saying, oh, but Planetside can do more players, and I say, but in a single battle, ugh.
Anyway, so I got some...
I did manage to get a handful of people to join my community.
And...
Maybe it's not the same.
Now it's, you know, it's got a...
Now it's like Star Wars space theme.
But you can still see some of the weirdness in that third image where there's a top-down view and you're in tunnels fighting monsters.
That's not in the current game, but the top-down view is still in there.
It's just as simple.
But basically, it has always been some kind of super big multiplayer experience, right?
Yeah, well it started out as a multiplayer shooter with giant monkey heads before the Kirby ball thing.
And over time, I increased the number of players.
The first test was actually Austin, Texas
to some business hotel in China.
My brother-in-law was in China.
We did the first network test.
I built the network system from scratch.
I had a background in programming,
in a network program in particular.
So I was like, oh, nobody's doing an indie multiplayer game.
Let me do an indie multiplayer game.
The reason nobody knows indie multiplayer is because they all fail.
So there's this curse of the multiplayer game.
But over time, I slowly, like, you know, I'm a performance junkie,
so I kept working on it.
Let's make it more scalable, we'll make it more scalable.
I didn't have 700 people to play with,
so I rented a bunch of machines to do that test.
But I did get a small group of people,
including one of my, a guy from New Zealand who was into PlanetSide 1,
and he didn't like PlanetSide 2,
so he's going to play this game instead of PlanetSide 2.
And I had a lady from MMO Massively OP who really liked it, who was the one who wrote the article.
I need to talk to her again.
And I will say one funny thing.
There was a...
It was a...
I got a comment from some guy on Twitter that had like hundreds of thousands of followers.
I think he did the music for Minecraft.
And it was him and his friends just making fun of the game saying,
Oh!
what's the point of so many players, what's the point of having a faction that can make...
C147? 417?
I shouldn't say that, but we ended up making friends.
But yeah, it had some highs and some lows, but at the end of the day I was glad I got it out of my shell
and put the game out there, even though the reception may not have been what I expected,
but I really did know what I was doing.
But I got those players to play, and while it was not a lot of them,
they were very dedicated, they watched the stream.
They joined a community and they played for years.
One of them is still a moderator in the current community.
And they got me to see things from a new perspective
and really help motivate me.
Because again, I mainly stayed at home.
The next thing that really changed for the community
was when I discovered Discord.
And I did try mailing lists, a lot of the traditional stuff,
going to conventions.
None of that stuff worked. Posting in forums, you know, I did try to reach out to people,
but it really didn't work in any scalable manner. So it was just a handful of us.
And then when Discord came out, you know, creating Discord doesn't do anything,
but what I did is I joined all the Discord servers I could find that had something to do with gaming,
and they would have looking for game groups, and I would say,
Hey, anybody want to play HunterNet?
It means legitimate thing, and they say, what the heck is that?
And I say, well, yes, this game, check it out.
And eventually I say, it's my game, you want to play?
And then, so I slowly collected people that way.
And within a few weeks, the community
tripled in size from seven to.
But it grew, and we got our first,
and we got some really, and people were really interested,
and they're really passionate.
We had our first five moderators from those early days,
and they're still with me.
Then the other really big kick
that really helped grow the community is HIO.
When I was in Austin, I did go to the,
Austin has a great indie development community.
It's just bigger, and I think it's more intimidating maybe.
Adam Saltzman, really famous guy in the indie game community, he did a talk when he was
working on Overland, and he talked about how he was going to do HIO, and he was one of
the first games on HIO.
HIO did like an early access kind of thing, like first access I think they called it.
Yeah, first access.
And he was really promoting that, and he had seen the crazy trailer, so he knew about my
game.
That was one good thing about the game being crazy is that people who saw it would tend to remember you if you talked to them later.
Actually, we had Adam talking about Overland here. He was on the screen.
Yeah.
Since moving from Austin, but he was one of the pinnacles of like, one of the cores of the community to help organize things and things.
But he gave a talk about HIO and how awesome it was.
So that was a huge help, just knowing about it.
Because who knows how much later I would have found out about it.
Once I got the game on itch.io, then it's free.
And I wasn't ready to go, especially after that.
And that was with that experience with people being,
what the heck is this?
I didn't want to go on Steam and get, you know,
it's intimidating to go on Steam, right?
People can be a little bit harsh.
So HIO just sounded perfect.
I put the game on HIO.
Before putting it on HIO, I changed the style to sci-fi,
spacious kind of thing.
And I changed the gameplay a bit, too.
It was moving in that direction.
It sort of gradually morphed into a space game.
And in HIO, it's been downloaded 16,000 times now.
And every week, I haven't really advertised it because I
I'm kind of happy with the slow, steady growth.
I don't want to be overwhelmed by managing more people than I have to before I'm ready.
But, you know, I have Discord all over the game.
Like, there's a voice bot in the game that says,
Please join Discord and talk to my creator!
When you fly in, there's big Star Wars style letters.
Come join us on Discord!
When you go to the command screen, there's Discord everywhere.
So I funnel everything through the Discord, and we get people donating Discord little by little.
And we use Discord, we have a bot, we have multiple bots, one of our moderators is working on the bot.
It advertises the streams, and it's been...
Without Discord and HIO, it would have been a lot harder.
Now I get plenty of feedback, and I have testers,
and I feel it's been good.
I actually have a few more things
to say about early Discord.
So really quickly, so Discord, I just
triggered some memories right now.
Two quick things.
Content creators, you have Twitch and YouTube
are the main ones right now.
I think that we got successful because of Twitch players and YouTubers early in the day, but Twitch more than ever.
And so these streamers, content creators, you want to pull them into your Discord, you want to spoil them too.
You can give them some free keys, it shouldn't cost you anything, and give them more than once.
So maybe one for them, one for their friends, one to give away.
And that has been a really big thing as well.
And you invite them to your Discord and...
you give them a special role.
And you want to make them feel special.
Because they are special.
They're promoting your game.
It's a nice win-win situation going on.
You actually have like 30 content creators online right
now.
Yeah, we have over 100, maybe around almost exactly 100
known content creators in our Discord.
And so we'll have a Discord content creator chat
as well where we can.
We can talk to them directly.
We can ping them all at the same time
and say, hey, we have this special promotion going on.
They can collaborate with each other.
Sometimes they'll have group ones
where they'll voice chat with each other.
So that really helps exposure, especially really early.
And then the second thing that really helped us early
to get people is Reddit.
And Reddit, it's a very unique crowd.
It'll take years to actually know how to talk.
properly to Redditors, with the Redd- Redd-Kit, is what they call it.
And it's a- it's a very different way to talk to people.
You can't just go out there and be like, say,
hey, look at my game, it's awesome.
No, it is- everyone will just, you know, download it,
you'll get negative karma, everyone will hate you,
and a lot of people will hate you, folks.
But, um, once you get used to Reddit, it's a wonderful place.
These are, like, real humans, and
the- what's cool about this is, um-
Early, we had a free key giveaway called Veteran Status.
So just before we launched, for one week, maybe it was two
weeks, we had a big, I think we used Glean.io to give away
our keys.
And we just gave away tons and tons of keys for this
duration.
And so if you post it in the right places, you can Google
giveaway sections, giveaway subreddits.
And there's maybe about five or six that are.
pretty legit.
There are bots watching it.
And so if you get pretty popular in a post,
a bot will pick it up.
And do you guys use IFTTT?
There are IFTTT bots that are watching these subreddits
that will email your post to maybe 20, 30,000 people.
And so all these people will get delivered the key.
We had our huge first burst in Discord.
by an IFTTT bot triggering.
And I didn't even know about it.
I was signed up to get email alerts from this bot.
That's how I knew.
And I got an alert.
I'm like, oh, wait a second, I got an alert.
And you can go to ifttt.com,
and if you look at the recipes,
you can see how many people are subscribed to these recipes.
And so the Reddit one for free key, it's very popular.
I get free keys all the time.
I think back then there were 18,000 people following it.
And so now there's probably, you know,
it might be even like 80,000, 100,000,
just for posting your free key giveaway.
So that really helped us in the early days.
Steam giveaways.
Not all of these are the best ones though.
It's been a while since I used it.
My favorite Reddit is reddit.com slash r slash game dev.
And they post all the time.
The game dev was pretty obvious.
Yeah, this one's pretty obvious.
But if you forget the list of legit ones to give away, just
Oh, they have a list here, right?
I am almost positive I saw a list here
of the best giveaway ones.
They have a really useful sidebar.
Yeah, maybe it's somewhere here.
FAQs somewhere.
You'll find it. If you search for it, you'll spend no longer than five minutes, you'll find it.
So I guess, actually I also want to talk to Ed about this because
I was speaking in Android 4.0 a bit for a moment.
所以因為他們三個遊戲剛好都是多了連線或是有Early Access
所以其實這樣子的遊戲的...
算是推廣方式跟單人單機或是說那種有劇情主線的遊戲其實
推廣方式會很不一樣
那我現在...因為剛好我們最後一位
就是剛進來的...就是最後進來的這位講者
他做的遊戲我們剛好看到是一個JRPG
是一個Cyberpunk JRPG
那他就不是多人
他可能也沒有Early Access
那這樣的情況下就是
狀況很不一樣
我想請教說他的想法是什麼
your game is different from early access games or multiplayer games?
Yeah, it's not multiplayer, it's very story-driven.
So, I know you mentioned this recently, right?
Don't worry about it's story-driven, just get it out there, get people playing it,
and then you can work on those people's feedback about the story and stuff,
and then improve it and make it better.
But there's also like the fear of...
Oh, if I put it out and those people play it, and then you update it, they're not going to go back and play what they've already played over again.
I think it's a fear that I need to get over and just put whatever I have out and not worry.
if your goal is to make the best possible game you can make, then the easiest way to
get there is to get feedback from real people. And just because you give away the game for
free or just because you spoil it for some users, does not shrink your market.
because the market is infinite.
There are how many hundred million people on Steam who buy games?
We as indies will never hit that 100 million cap.
Our game is pretty big for indie and we hit 3 million.
And I guarantee you there's another 3 million people out there
who would buy the game if they only heard about it.
No one's heard about your game, right? That's the number one problem.
And the other problem is, are you working on the right stuff?
So I truly believe that you just get more value out of putting it out there,
being open and collecting the feedback and then working on that feedback,
than you lose by spoiling it to some people,
or because those people will now not buy your game, right?
How many keys did you give away?
We gave away...
probably
probably about one third of
the activations are probably all giveaways and
you know everything
every time you give away a key... So it's more than ten thousand, I guess?
Yeah, it's more than ten thousand keys that we've given away in total
and especially as an online game
you know, you want people to play with their friends.
So when you give away a key to one person,
and then they'll drag their friend in,
and they'll drag their friend in.
It's just a pyramid.
So there, just like he said, there's an infinite pool of people.
And I mean, that's a multiplayer game,
you have a single player game,
but that sells.
They were here at TGF.
That's a single player game.
They gave away 10,000 keys as well, right?
And they sold 1 million additional copies.
It's not like you give away a key for free and then you lose.
You print free money.
If you give the keys to the right people who have an audience,
like the content creators, then it just slows down.
Elsa has something to say.
This is my wife Elsa, the co-founder of Throne of Lies.
So we did a giveaway, really really big giveaway last December.
and we're working with content creator YoggCast.
Can you speak Chinese?
Yeah, but I want to respect them too.
We give away a lot.
We were even thinking about, damn, should we give that much?
Because they asked for so much.
But in the end, we decided to give away that much to YoggCast.
And it actually brings a lot from Africa.
YoggCast is the YouTuber YoggCast.
These people, right?
Yeah.
Yeah, these people.
These people, yeah.
We... I'm not sure if I'm... I don't think I can say the exact number, but it was more than 10,000 keys.
Just for the event?
Just for the event, yeah. It was tens of thousands of keys.
But just because we give those away doesn't mean they're all going to use it.
And a lot of them will activate it and they'll just let it rot.
I know I haven't played half of my library, but eventually they will.
And the thing is, every time they see your game, it puts a seed in the back of their mind.
It's just like, you know, when you see Coca-Cola ads, why do they spend so much money so that you can see it for one second?
It's because eventually you'll think about it, and if you see little hints and pieces of it, it'll remind you.
It's just, everything's psychology.
Mm-hmm.
Okay.
Sorry, I wasn't ready.
Like that!
Advice taken.
Give me a couple of weeks to fix things up and I'll...
I think you do want to avoid giving these things to press, right?
Yeah, I think part of my worry is giving it to press early and also I'm still looking for funding
and I don't know if putting it out in early access, as it were, is going to affect any future relationships with publishers or...
money people, they're like, oh well, you know, just put it out and it's not... I don't know,
if it... maybe people don't like it and they're like, oh well. I don't know, they're like,
you know, if that's not part of their plan of putting it out in early access, then, I
don't know. Maybe that's the basic...
Um...
I don't have money. I do not.
Laughter
We're all...
We're all looking for money, right?
Laughter
I, I, I have...
There's a point.
So my minimum...
I'm not sure if it would be in NT
but...
like 160,000
pounds.
Okay.
So let's say 200,000 US dollars.
Yeah.
How much money do you burn each month?
Not like one package, because 200,000, that is what you calculate you need to finish the game, right?
Yes.
So, ok, forget about that calculation.
Give me the number of money you need every month to keep going.
How much would that be?
I don't understand the difference.
Like, there is no difference.
I just want to go, like, the 200,000 lasted for how many years?
Uh, that's like 18 months.
So that's me and freelance artists and blah blah blah.
So here's the point.
I mean, I can continue working on this.
So you don't necessarily need the money?
At some point I will need the money to pay the contractors for the art that I cannot do myself.
The point I'm trying to make is that you can absolutely sell an unfinished game, right?
And a few people will buy it.
You will not get 200,000 from launching it on Early Access, but you will get some amount of money.
And if the game is any good and you keep working on it and you keep iterating on the feedback,
at least that's my opinion, there is a fair chance that next month more people will buy
it than the previous month.
And so whatever your money is that you're looking for every month, your burndown money
basically, there is a good chance that on Early Access you can hit that amount of money.
And then you can develop the game forever.
That was what happened to us.
When we launched Early Access, we were below that threshold.
But then once the streamers picked it up,
and it became more and more known,
and they took it and carried it out into the world,
more people, enough people were buying the game every month
that money was coming in, that enough money was coming in
so that we could just continue paying our developers.
As long as that money is coming in every month, we could go forever.
That is the alternative business model that I'm proposing, in a way.
Because if you do that, you don't need a publisher.
You don't have to give away your IP, you don't have to give away your revenue.
You're truly indie if you do that.
It's truly scary, so I would like to hear your opinion on that.
I agree with you mostly, I think if you have a bit of a wrong way to begin with.
I think in my situation that seems hard to me because to create more content and keep
the interest and to get those early access sales, I need to pay people to do art and
things to make new stuff for people to play.
I do not have the money.
to pay those people and it's very unlikely that I would be able to generate enough money
from sales to do that.
Right, so you're saying the 200,000 that you want, you would actually not spend them on
yourself but you would hire people for that money to help you finish the job?
I mean, a large chunk of that, yes.
I see.
So if I had like, say...
I don't know, 10, 20,000.
That would give me enough of a run up to generate,
or start generating content that I could then
be updating the game with.
As I go, there's like a little initial hump
that I need to get over to them.
Does that make sense?
Yes, a lot of it makes sense.
I think everyone in this room knows about initial humps.
I may have a solution to your problem.
Oop!
Shuffle.
This is getting exciting.
Okay, so...
We were just thinking about the shuffle.
Are you rich?
I'm not rich.
Sorry, sorry again, once more.
However, what you can do is profit share.
And it's not the most popular thing, but we did profit share.
Our current artist is profit share.
and uh... you know we we started off with a decent amount of profit share
and that really helped us. You have to find someone that's uh...
very dedicated and passionate about your project
I want to pay people
like not not not, that sounds very rude actually, I'm sorry
uh... yeah
I personally think
profit share fine but you need to pay them a base wage
beforehand. I'm not going to ask someone to work for free on my game
with the chance that there's no money at the end of it.
But the thing is, you're also working on this game with the chance there's no money at the end of it.
Yeah, but that's fine. I've got contract work that I can pay my own bills with.
I guess the biggest difference is that if you're going to contractors,
then most of the contractors basically expect to be paid up front.
I think this is a norm, right?
It's a different kind of contract. It's a contractor.
But I mean, if you met people who are actually really very enthusiastic about your project,
and they're actually willing to jump onto the ship with the idea that I may not get any money out of it,
or maybe very less, instead of getting paid up front.
then basically, I wouldn't officially say these guys are contractors.
Basically, they are on your ship.
And so...
They're basically partners.
Yeah, they're basically partners.
There is another game that actually did something like this.
Armello.
Oh, this guy's great.
So Armello actually have a formal...
So Armello actually have a...
正式的祭典方式
就是說
他把很多contract找來
然後他就把他用正式的祭典方式說
我做這件工作是多少點
我做這件工作多少點
然後他們到最後可以
就是用這個公平的點數計算方式
去最後來分錢
來分他們的revenue
那
可是我其實是有問過這個
因為他們其實有來過台灣呃
應該不只一次
然後我也在其他場合遇過他們
那他們的講法是說
因為他們的遊戲基本上其實是撥Game
撥Game然後數位化
那其實他們絕大部分的像遊戲規則
之類的東西
其實在紙上已經實驗完了
然後他才說
喔我之後要數位化
所以我需要多少人去畫
什麼100張卡牌
我要多少人去產生地圖
所以
他
I remember I asked him, and he said that about 60-70% of the game content
was already done when he was doing the action of unboxing the package.
And there were very few changes afterwards.
So I think, my point is that there definitely are like...
sort of like successful stories from this kind of game that, you know,
they have a very good revenue share system.
That actually, you know, is...
You can see the spreadsheet, how much is going to be paid to this person based on revenue share.
They have a very formal system of it.
But this is still the only case I've heard about.
I mean, they also got a lot of money from Indie Bundle.
Yeah, that's true. But I don't know if that's up front or later.
That might be later.
I think it's later, because they started working with contractors before Indie Bundle.
I know their IndieFund announcement, but that's like only a very little time before they actually launch.
I think asking people to essentially work for free with maybe the promise of profit share later is...
this is my project.
Like, it's hard, like, if I was starting something
and they had a chance to have a lot of input on it
from early on, then maybe it would be different.
But just asking someone to like,
oh hey, come do what I tell you on this thing,
like, is hard.
And, like, I,
having asked people to do stuff.
for free previously, it's like, well, they might do it,
you might have to poke them loads, and then you feel bad
because they're doing it for free.
And it's hard to get people's best work out of them
or get them to dedicate the time I found it.
I wanted to say that this is sort of getting
to business strategy, right?
And I think something we really need to keep in mind is that
Every game is different, and things have been changing very quickly in this.
I want to push back a little bit in the indie sphere.
I think Early Access worked really well for Subnautica,
what you guys did with Game of Lives worked really well, but...
On Discord, I'm in lots of groups of other developers
that have tried to do their multiplayer shooter on Early Access,
their other thing, and you see that the advice that worked like a year ago, or even months
ago doesn't necessarily work anymore.
I think that it's good to look at what you should go out there and look at what other
people have done and what's successful to them, but you really have to be careful and
see how things have changed and how your project is different.
Different funding models are going to work better for different games, and I think with
Ed's game.
If he just put it on early access right now, I would definitely predict that
he's going to have the discoverability problem number one.
Nobody's going to even know that it's on early access.
The amount of money he's going to be able to generate is just not going to be enough to pay anything.
They say now, for a lot of gamers,
your early access launch is your launch. It can be really difficult
to get, I'm not going to give any numbers, but I know a really
successful game that just...
came out at the end of 2018, and yeah, they thought they were going to get a big bump.
And they're a really well-known indie game, and they got a small fraction of the Steam
front page attention that they did not that long ago when they did their early access
launch.
And this is a big game.
This is already...
Going in as an indie is like doing a start.
You have to assume that one in ten, I don't know what numbers, are going to fail.
And that could be you.
If you only look at the successes and think, oh, by what they did, it's going to...
that's really important because if you do want to do sharing,
you know, get an artist involved, they need to be compassionate about your work.
Nobody's going to be compassionate about it if they haven't seen it.
And what I would do, if I were you, is go on Discord and do similar to what I did.
Go join communities having to do with Japanese stuff, and there are a lot of them.
I got some of my players from, like, anime groups that had nothing to do with space games.
And you can talk to them individually.
Because you've got to start small.
When you're trying to scale, nobody's...
Go and talk to them and say, hey, you want to check out this game?
I can give you access to it.
You don't even have to be on HIO.
You can give them a direct link.
And from those people, you're going to get feedback.
And because you gave them personal attention,
they might say, hey, I can become your moderator,
or I can help talk to my friends that are really
into this style of game.
And it's not the same.
From those people, you might find people
that could become partners and work with you.
And I think that's the way.
I think the main takeaway from this is that don't be afraid to actually give your game to people that you might not know beforehand.
I mean, showing your game is always good and it's easy to forget that.
Like taking it to events or like today.
我爸爸也有,如果你們想看看我玩的遊戲的話
我爸爸有教過我
我會...
我會... 解釋一下
我會... 解釋一下 從其他的印尼玩家來的知識
就是...
其實蠻久以前
就是有蠻多美國的印尼
有講過一個概念是說
就是...
你在Steam上
只需要賣給0%的玩家
你的遊戲就可以...應該說
就是你的遊戲只要賣給在Steam上0%的玩家
你的遊戲其實就有機會活得下來
那這個前提是因為
其實你獨立遊戲就算賣得再多
你的coverage通常也大概都是Steam user的0.幾%而已
那這個數據的另外一個面向的意思是說
一定有這麼多人還...他就是完全沒有聽過你的遊戲
所以...
沒有道理說 因為我怕我的遊戲給別人看
所以我就故意什麼都不講
或者是說我怕可能有人會抄我的idea
或者是說有人會覺得說我現在做得不好
他以後不想再跟我講話之類的
就是理論上這種概念應該是不太存在的
就是你永遠有新的人可以去講
然後你永遠有新的人可以去認識
那在銷售上來說的話就是
其實你永遠有新的銷售對象
那只是問題是說
一開始的那個最早的那小撮人
你要怎麼去找到
那可能他們可以幫你去做宣傳
類似像這樣的事情
所以
Yeah, I guess that's what I'm trying to say
that, you know, like
the 0% analogy is that
basically you can
just you can survive just by selling to 0% of the Steam user.
You can actually still survive because there are so many players there
and also it means that there are
almost 100% of the players that just
never heard about your game before so you should not be afraid of
you know like, oh my game is going to leak out there
and you know they will pirate it or
copy my ID or things like that.
So, I guess that's actually a very long discussion about discoverability and survivability, I guess.
So, I guess I want to close down with, I want to just do a closing with a bit more casual question.
So, can you guys tell the audience that maybe just one game, you can say, I've been playing this game.
for maybe a couple of months in the past, or maybe
a few, one or two years in the past, and I think that game's good, you should check out the game
and why. Like just, name one game and say something about it.
I may take the game that
some others may be thinking about too, but Magic the Gathering
Arena, I've been really enjoying it. Sorry folks. Magic the Gathering Arena, it's...
I've always been a big trading card game fan, so I've played a lot of Hearthstone for years.
And eventually, you know, in high school I used to play Magic the Gathering all the time
with my friends.
And apparently after playing Arena, a lot of our rules were wrong, that we thought they
were.
So we weren't really playing it the right way, apparently.
But it was still fun.
Their friend system isn't very good yet, but it'll get there.
But it's very polished.
Every single button will have a cool animation around it.
And even when you're hovering over cards,
there'll be a separate subtle sound hovering over all of them.
They all have a separate sound effect when you play it.
Something's really satisfying about it
whenever you play a card or even just
even just at the beginning of the match.
Or over time, when you have your set,
you can browse your whole set, sort of like Hearthstone,
and look at it in awe.
There's something about it where I played the previous match
at the Gathering on lines where it was like Duel
of the Planeswalkers.
And I wasn't a fan.
It was OK for maybe like a week for me.
And then after that, I'm a bit bored.
And you have limited cards.
But here, they try to copy the experience of as if you're
just playing on a real tabletop.
They'll even, for those familiar with instant cards,
you can even pause.
There's a little pause in between to play your instant
cards each time, which, when you start, it can be a little
bit annoying, but you get used to it fast.
Overall, I've really been enjoying it.
So you think most of the aspects you say about this game is better than the same aspects in Hearthstone, right?
Yeah, I like them both, but right now I currently like Magic the Gathering Arena.
Maybe it's just a change of pace because I've been playing Hearthstone for years, or maybe it's high school nostalgia.
Okay.
Jonas?
I'll skip for now.
I'm like I've been playing that game since it came out in like small bursts
like since moving to Taiwan I only got a PlayStation 4 yesterday after I had to
sell my UK one because it wouldn't work here so I have been sustaining myself on
collecting all the little tree guys
Yeah, I got like 700 out of 900 and it's getting difficult now.
But I just love that world. It's still after like, oh man, I don't even know how many hours I've played.
Maybe like 600 hours or something.
I still just love running around and doing stuff in that game. It's cool.
I can totally imagine that.
How about Fernando?
Yeah, I played that game a lot too, I love it.
But another Nintendo game, I would say Super Smash Bros.
I've been playing a lot of that.
I played it with my brother-in-law, who's ex-marine, and makes us do push-ups whenever we lose.
So if you don't want to lose, yeah.
20 push-ups, or 20 squats, and you're real sore the next day if you lose a lot.
And that game actually influenced HunterNet a lot. Not this one, but the older ones.
And I thought, well, Nintendo's cute, I like cute.
So that's like my Kirby flying multiplayer shooter idea,
but I learned that only Nintendo is really good at doing Q-pit.
It's really hard to do it yourself.
But even until today, you play HunterNet, the new space
version, there's abilities in there
that were influenced by Smash Brothers.
In particular, in Smash Brothers,
you have the omnidirectional shields.
And in HunterNet, you have an absorb shield and a repel.
I can definitely see that now, because there are like 50 or 100 different items in Smash Bros. that each character can use.
And basically you sort of internalize that into the system you need to put onto the ship before battle.
Basically it's the same thing, right?
Yeah, and there's also, you know, when I made HunterNet, especially when I was going in the space direction,
I played, you know, one of the first games I bought was X-Wing for DOS back in like 1993.
And in my opinion, and I play a lot of flight simulators, that's probably the game I put on the death stat, is Isle 2 Stormovic.
Oh my god, yes.
And space games are just not, they don't have the depth of a flight simulator because they're missing gravity,
and you don't have energy fighting, the flight models just don't make sense.
And Smash Brothers, if you play 100Net today you'll notice that I, you can tell that I took some ideas from fighting games,
and mixed them into space combat.
to create a space combat game that, just like a good fighting game, can be fun.
One versus one in an empty rectangle, or in this case, an empty cube.
So yeah, Smash Bros. has been a huge inspiration and it's still one of my favorite games.
Very interesting.
Two games that I enjoyed last year was...
One is a ROM hack of the original Zelda game from the past for the Super Nintendo.
So apparently there are people out there who...
You can play the original Zelda A Link to the Past on an emulator, right?
Everyone does that.
But apparently there are clever people out there who have figured out how to hack the ROM of Zelda
and just make a completely new Zelda game with the original A Link to the Past.
graphics and music, and just the world is different and the story is different, and the dungeons are different, right?
And they are actually good.
Like, I was very surprised by the level of polish.
It's not Nintendo level of polish, but it's incredibly good.
Do you know which ROM packs? I assume there are many ROM packs in the game.
Oh, which one?
Parallel Worlds.
And the other game that I've enjoyed great this year was Factorio.
Oh, Factorio.
Especially with friends, because there are not too many base-building or economy-building games out there that are multiplayer.
And I kind of like Farm Simulator or something.
But Factorio just...
a thing to do while you hang out with your friends and you just chat in Discord and you
build up your factory a little bit.
But it can also be super intense and challenging.
If you haven't heard about the game, it's phenomenal.
And they are in early access, I believe.
They've been working on it for many, many years.
It's a very small studio in Eastern Europe.
Taipei Game Show.
Oh, they did?
Like, 2017, I think.
Yeah.
So, like, their first game show ever was actually in Taipei Game Show.
Nice.
Yeah.
Did you personally meet them?
Yeah, I talked to them.
Are they nice?
Yeah, they are really nice.
Can you introduce me to them?
Yeah, actually, we also have an indie developer that is...
super fan of Factorio and he went on to take pictures with them and
talk at length about the game with the developers.
I think they actually got a very good experience out of the WCG.
So actually we have been running for like 90 minutes, so I guess it's a good time to call it.
如果大家想要跟我們聊天的話
如果大家想要展示什麼東西的話
就跟我們聊聊看吧
就這樣吧
那我們先間斷休息一下
那等一下有兩位在場的朋友
他可能想要借用前面的投影機
來秀一下他們想要介紹的東西
那我們就大概花個十分鐘上個廁所
然後大家可以喝個茶這樣子
先感謝今天大家的參與
所以我會跟觀眾說,如果有任何作品想要秀,你要給前面的宇團人看,還是你要秀給其他朋友,都隨意這樣。
好,那就請大家掌聲鼓勵這些宇團人這樣子。